YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series III. Public Advocacy
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY
  - Subseries B. Program Subject Files
    - Ethnic Groups
      - African Americans
        - Race relations and the YWCA
          - Dodge Hotel interracial practices, 1933-36 (Box 426, Folder 10)
          - Race relations advisory group, 1946-50 (Box 426, Folder 11)
        - Scottsboro Case, 1931-48 (Box 426, Folder 12)
        - Segregation
          - and integration in education
            - General, 1931-73, n.d. (Box 426, Folder 13-14)
            - School busing, 1971-76 (Box 427, Folder 1-2)
          - in Washington, D.C., 1948-53 (Box 427, Folder 3)
          - in transportation, 1942-50 (Box 427, Folder 4)
      - American Indians
        - General, 1931-73, n.d. (Box 427, Folder 5-6)
        - Handbook of Federal Indian Law, Mar 1940 (Box 427, Folder 7)
      - Asian-Pacific peoples
        - Repeal of exclusion laws affecting eastern hemisphere Indians, Filipinos, 1928-46 (Box 427, Folder 8)
        - Repeal of exclusion laws affecting the Chinese, Koreans, 1940-49 (Box 427, Folder 9)
        - Japanese/Japanese Americans
          - Japanese Exclusion Clause, 1922-35 (Box 427, Folder 10)
          - World War II Relocation and Resettlement
            - General, 1942-52, 1981, n.d. (Box 427, Folder 11-14)
            - YWCA Japanese Evacuee Project, Jan 1942- Sep 1946: report by Esther Briesemeister (Box 427, Folder 15-16)
          - Molly Kitajima case, 1946-47 (Box 427, Folder 17)
      - The Foreign Born
        - General, 1926-69 (Box 428, Folder 1-11)
        - Alien registration, 1925-42 (Box 428, Folder 12-13)
        - Deportation, 1926-40 (Box 429, Folder 1-2)
        - Separated families 1922-40 (Box 429, Folder 3)
        - Reference Materials
          - Common Council of American Unity, 1951-52 (Box 429, Folder 4)
          - National Committee on Immigration Policy, n.d. (Box 429, Folder 5-6)
          - Third Special Conference, Immigration and Naturalization Service in Conjunction with National Conference on Citizenship, n.d. (Box 429, Folder 7)
      - Jewish Americans
        - Anti-Semitism, 1942-60 (Box 429, Folder 8-9)
        - National Council of Jewish Women, National Committee on Social Legislation, 1943-44 (Box 429, Folder 10)
      - Mexican- and Latin-Americans
        - General
          - 1943-51, 1969 (Box 429, Folder 11-12)
          - 1970-71 (Box 430, Folder 1)
        - Puerto Rico, 1944-51 (Box 430, Folder 2)
      - Refugees
        - General, 1922-42 (Box 430, Folder 3-4)
        - YWCA National Committee on Refugees, 1938-39 (Box 430, Folder 5)
    - Government and politics
      - Citizenship
        - General, 1924-65, 1995 (Box 430, Folder 6)
        - Voter participation, 1983-99 (Box 430, Folder 7)
      - Congress
        - Appropriations, 1939-53, 1995 (Box 430, Folder 8-10)
        - Blocs in Congress, 1943-44 (Box 430, Folder 11-12)
        - Congressional reform, proposed YWCA resolution, 1964 (Box 430, Folder 13)
        - Filibuster
          - 1946-53 (Box 430, Folder 14-15)
          - 1955-59 (Box 431, Folder 1)
      - Federal-state relations, 1958-65 (Box 431, Folder 2)
      - Political party platforms, 1948-88 (Box 431, Folder 3-6)
      - Politics and political action, 1956-67, 1992 (Box 431, Folder 7)
      - Presidents, 1956-69 (Box 431, Folder 8)
      - Reorganization of federal government, 1945-60 (Box 431, Folder 9-12)
      - Supreme Court
        - General, 1971-75 (Box 431, Folder 13)
        - Nomination of G. Harrold Carswell, 1970 (Box 431, Folder 14)
    - International relations
      - General, 1930-53 (Box 431, Folder 15)
      - Human welfare
        - History and general reference, 1938, 1950 (Box 431, Folder 16)
        - Africa (Angola, Biafra/Nigeria, South Africa), 1958-78 (Box 431, Folder 17)
        - Bretton Woods Agreement, 1944-46 (Box 432, Folder 1)
        - European Recovery Program/Marshall Plan
          - General, 1947-50 (Box 432, Folder 2-4)
          - Aid to Britain/Lend-Lease Bill, 1941-46 (Box 432, Folder 5)
          - British Loan, 1946 (Box 432, Folder 6)
        - Germany, 1946-59 (Box 432, Folder 7)
        - Greece and Turkey, 1947 (Box 432, Folder 8)
        - Human Rights, International Covenant/Declaration, 1946-68 (Box 432, Folder 9-14)
        - India, 1951-58 (Box 432, Folder 15)
        - Information and Cultural Exchange program, 1944-61 (Box 432, Folder 16)
        - International Development Association (IDA), 1974 (Box 433, Folder 1)
        - International Labor Organization (ILO), 1930-77 (Box 433, Folder 2-3)
        - Korea, 1949-53 (Box 433, Folder 4)
        - Latin America, 1927-39 (Box 433, Folder 5-6)
        - Mutual security/Foreign Aid, 1952-71 (Box 433, Folder 7-11)
        - Narcotics, 1921-32 (Box 433, Folder 12)
        - National YWCA Institute: The Web of Racism and its International Dimensions, 1970-71 (Box 433, Folder 13)
        - Nestle boycott, 1980-92, n.d. (Box 433, Folder 14)
        - Pan American cooperation
          - General, 1940-45 (Box 433, Folder 15)
          - Monroe Doctrine, 1923-63, n.d. (Box 433, Folder 16)
        - "Point Four" Program for World Economic Progress Through Cooperative Technical Assistance, 1949-55 (Box 434, Folder 1-3)
        - Refugees and Relief, 1938-73 (Box 434, Folder 4-8)
        - Slavery, 1928-36 (Box 434, Folder 9)
        - South Africa, 1964-86 (Box 434, Folder 10)
        - Soviet Union, 1937-58 (Box 434, Folder 11)
        - Spain, 1944-50 (Box 434, Folder 12-13)
        - Surplus food, "Food for Peace," 1955-75 (Box 434, Folder 14)
        - Turkey, 1922-27 (Box 434, Folder 15)
      - United Nations
        - General
          - 1945-46 (Box 434, Folder 16-17)
          - 1947-78 (Box 435, Folder 1-10)
        - Bricker Resolution
          - 1952-May 1953 (Box 435, Folder 11-13)
          - Jun 1953-57, 1973 (Box 436, Folder 1)
        - Conference on International Organization, 1945 (Box 436, Folder 2)
        - Economic and Social Council
          - General, 1946-56 (Box 436, Folder 3)
          - Status of Women Commission, 1945-68 (Box 436, Folder 4-5)
        - Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organizations (UNESCO), 1944-76 (Box 436, Folder 6-8)
        - Expanded Technical Assistance Program (UNETAP), 1954-59 (Box 436, Folder 9)
        - Food and Agricultural Organization (FAO), 1943-63 (Box 436, Folder 10-11)
        - Founding of
          - General, 1943-45 (Box 436, Folder 12-14)
          - Ratification of Treaties, 1943-44 (Box 436, Folder 15)
        - Human rights conventions, YWCA ratification drive, 1965-87 (Box 437, Folder 1)
        - International Children's Emergency Fund (UNICEF), 1947-77 (Box 437, Folder 2-4)
        - International Refugee Organization (IRO), 1946-52 (Box 437, Folder 5)
        - International Trade Organization (ITO), 1946-50 (Box 437, Folder 6)
        - International Women's Year, 1974-75, n.d. (Box 437, Folder 7-8)
        - North Atlantic Treaty (NATO), 1949-52 (Box 437, Folder 9-10)
        - Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA)
          - 1940-Apr 1946 (Box 437, Folder 11-14)
          - May 1946-Dec 1947 (Box 438, Folder 1-4)
        - Women United for United Nations, 1946-47 (Box 438, Folder 5)
        - World Health Organization, 1947-53 (Box 438, Folder 6)
      - Vietnam, 1965-75 (Box 438, Folder 7)
      - White House Conference on International Cooperation, 1965-66 (Box 438, Folder 8)
      - Women
        - Status of, 1935-38 (Box 438, Folder 9-10)
        - Traffic in women, 1933-37 (Box 438, Folder 11)
        - US follow up to UN Fourth World Conference on Women, 1996 (Box 438, Folder 12)
        - Women's Charter, 1936-38 (Box 438, Folder 13-14)
      - World Government, 1948-53 (Box 438, Folder 15)
      - World without War
        - General, 1941-56, n.d. (Box 439, Folder 1)
        - American policy
          - Bosnia, 1995 (Box 439, Folder 2)
          - China, 1920-72 (Box 439, Folder 3-4)
          - Ethiopian conflict, 1935-36 (Box 439, Folder 5)
          - Middle East and Far East, 1945-74, 1998 (Box 439, Folder 6)
          - Panama Canal, 1997-98 (Box 439, Folder 7)
          - Russia/Soviet Union, 1930-36, 1967 (Box 439, Folder 8)
          - Sino-Japanese conflict, 1931-43 (Box 439, Folder 9-11)
          - Spanish Civil War, 1936-39 (Box 439, Folder 12-13)
          - Vietnam, 1965-75 (Box 439, Folder 14-16)
        - Anti-ballistic missile system, 1969 (Box 440, Folder 1-2)
        - Atomic energy/weapons, 1945-74, n.d. (Box 440, Folder 3-9)
        - Cause and Cure of War conferences, 1924-40 (Box 440, Folder 10-11)
        - Displaced persons/Refugees
          - 1938-40 (Box 440, Folder 12)
          - 1941-51, n.d. (Box 441, Folder 1-9)
        - Foreign Policy Association, 1939, 1961-64 (Box 441, Folder 10)
        - Genocide, 1948-73 (Box 441, Folder 11-12)
        - International Cooperation Year (1965)
          - Correspondence, 1963-66 (Box 441, Folder 13)
          - Projects, 1965-66 (Box 441, Folder 14)
          - Pacem in Terris (Peace on Earth) International Convocation to examine the requirements for peace, 1965 (Box 442, Folder 1)
        - International Court of Justice (World Court), 1923-46, n.d. (Box 442, Folder 2-3)
        - League of Nations, 1923-40, n.d. (Box 442, Folder 4-5)
        - Limitation of armaments
          - General, 1921-77 (Box 442, Folder 6-14)
          - Poison gas, 1926-38 (Box 442, Folder 15)
        - Neutrality
          - General, 1935-41 (Box 443, Folder 1-5)
          - Aid to victims of aggression, 1937-40 (Box 443, Folder 6)
        - Pacifism and isolationism, 1935-40 (Box 443, Folder 7)
        - Peace
          - Peace and Disarmament Committee of the Women's International Organizations, 1931-38, n.d. (Box 443, Folder 8-9)
          - National Peace Conference, 1931-42 (Box 443, Folder 10-11)
          - Party platforms, 1932-52 (Box 443, Folder 12)
          - Peace pact (Kellogg-Briand treaty), 1927-28, 1934 (Box 443, Folder 13)
          - Peace and the YWCA, 1938, 1952-59 (Box 443, Folder 14-15)
          - People's Mandate to End War, 1935-36 (Box 443, Folder 16)
          - Role of Industrialists, 1935-38 (Box 444, Folder 1-2)
        - Peace corps, 1960-62 (Box 444, Folder 3)
        - Sanctions, 1926-39 (Box 444, Folder 4-5)
        - United Nations trusteeship
          - General, 1945-47 (Box 444, Folder 6)
          - South Africa, 1949-51 (Box 444, Folder 7)
        - Universal military training/Peacetime conscription, 1939-71, n.d. (Box 444, Folder 8-13)
        - War profits, 1935-39 (Box 444, Folder 14)
        - World economic conferences, 1927-39 (Box 444, Folder 15-16)
      - Morality and the media
        - Mass media, 1964-69 (Box 445, Folder 1)
        - Motion pictures, 1924-43 (Box 445, Folder 2-3)
        - Obscenity and pornography, 1971-73 (Box 445, Folder 4)
      - Public health and safety
        - General, 1937-99 (Box 445, Folder 5-8)
        - Breast and cervical cancer, 1984-97, n.d. (Box 445, Folder 9-12)
        - Food, Drugs, and Cosmetics, 1934-68 (Box 445, Folder 13-14)
        - Highway safety, May-Jul 1967 (Box 446, Folder 1)
        - Maternity and Infant Care, 1920-52 (Box 446, Folder 2-4)
        - Mental health, 1940-45, 1975 (Box 446, Folder 5)
        - Narcotics, 1932-56 (Box 446, Folder 6-13)
        - Nutrition, 1936-40, 1969-76 (Box 446, Folder 14)
        - Prostitution
          - Venereal disease, 1938-51 (Box 446, Folder 15-16)
          - White slave traffic, 1935-36 (Box 446, Folder 17)
        - Reproductive rights
          - Abortion
            - 1966-72 (Box 446, Folder 18-19)
            - 1973-98, n.d. (Box 447, Folder 1-5)
          - Birth control and world population, 1923-50, 1962-75, 1985 (Box 447, Folder 6-10)
        - Smoking and cigarettes, 1964-70 (Box 447, Folder 11)
        - Violence prevention, 1980-2000 (Box 447, Folder 12)
    - Science and the environment
      - Conservation
        - Flood control, 1947-57 (Box 448, Folder 1-2)
        - Highway Beautification bill, 1965 (Box 448, Folder 3)
        - Wilderness Act, 1962-68, n.d. (Box 448, Folder 4)
      - Energy crisis, 1974-76 (Box 448, Folder 5)
      - Environment, 1969, 1977 (Box 448, Folder 6)
      - Outer space, 1958-62 (Box 448, Folder 7)
    - Social and economic welfare
      - General, 1911-75 (Box 448, Folder 8)
      - Child welfare
        - Child Care/Day Care, 1942-99 (Box 448, Folder 9)
        - Child labor
          - General, 1922-69 (Box 448, Folder 10-13)
          - During wartime, 1940-46 (Box 448, Folder 14)
        - Children's Bureau, 1933-69, n.d. (Box 448, Folder 15-18)
        - Illegitimate children, 1973-74 (Box 449, Folder 1)
        - Maternal and child health and welfare, 1938, 1945-46 (Box 449, Folder 2)
        - School lunch, 1944-71 (Box 449, Folder 3-4)
      - Conference on Unfinished Business in Social Legislation, National Council of Jewish Women, May 1946 (Box 449, Folder 5)
      - Consumers
        - General, 1933-75 (Box 449, Folder 6-9)
        - Grade labeling, 1943-44 (Box 449, Folder 10)
      - Economic Opportunity
        - National Recovery Act, 1933-35 (Box 449, Folder 11-13)
        - Economic Opportunity Act/Office of Economic Opportunity
          - 1965-70 (Box 449, Folder 14-15)
          - 1971-74 (Box 450, Folder 1-3)
      - Employment training and vocational guidance
        - The aged, 1950-67 (Box 450, Folder 4)
        - Full and equal employment, 1941-79 (Box 450, Folder 5-10)
        - Household employment, 1928-64 (Box 450, Folder 11-14)
        - Unemployment, 1928-38 (Box 451, Folder 1-5)
        - United States Employment Services (USES) and Social Work Manpower Training Act, 1933-69 (Box 451, Folder 6-7)
        - Works Progress Administration (WPA) and National Youth Administration (NYA), 1936-42 (Box 451, Folder 8)
      - Health care and health insurance
        - 1933-47 (Box 451, Folder 9-15)
        - 1948-97, n.d. (Box 452, Folder 1-4)
      - Housing
        - General
          - 1936-49 (Box 452, Folder 5-13)
          - 1950-59, 1989 (Box 453, Folder 1-7)
        - Fair housing, 1945-71 (Box 453, Folder 8-11)
        - Homelessness, 1913, 1975-91 (Box 453, Folder 12)
        - Housing and Home Finance Agency, 1949 (Box 454, Folder 1-2)
        - Local associations and community housing problems, 1946-63 (Box 454, Folder 3)
        - Middle income housing, 1949-50 (Box 454, Folder 4)
        - National Public Housing Conference, Inc., 1946-50 (Box 454, Folder 5-9)
      - Hunger, 1969 (Box 454, Folder 10)
      - Labor
        - YWCA historical summaries, 1956, 1962 (Box 454, Folder 11)
        - Agricultural migrant workers
          - General
            - 1942-60 (Box 454, Folder 12-15)
            - 1961-76 (Box 455, Folder 1-3)
          - United Farm Workers, 1970-76 (Box 455, Folder 4-5)
        - Continental Congress of Workers and Farmers for Economic Reconstruction, 1932-34 (Box 455, Folder 6)
        - Disability law, 1951-52 (Box 455, Folder 7)
        - Labor Advisory Group, 1946-47 (Box 455, Folder 8)
        - Labor education, Labor Extension Bill, 1947-48 (Box 455, Folder 9)
        - Labor movement, 1937-72 (Box 455, Folder 10-13)
        - National defense
          - Maintenance of fair labor standards in industry, 1939-45 (Box 455, Folder 14)
          - Migration, 1941-43 (Box 455, Folder 15)
          - Protection of organized labor, 1940-44 (Box 455, Folder 16)
        - National Labor Relations Act, 1935-42 (Box 456, Folder 1-2)
        - Nike, Inc.'s labor practices, 1996-98 (Box 456, Folder 3-4)
        - Right of workers to organize
          - General, 1928-34, 1978 (Box 456, Folder 5)
          - White collar workers, 1934-50 (Box 456, Folder 6-7)
        - Southern Council on Women and Children in Industry, 1929-33 (Box 456, Folder 8)
        - Strikes
          - General, 1947-50 (Box 456, Folder 9)
          - Brooklyn YWCA strike, 1946-47 (Box 456, Folder 10-12)
        - U.S. Dept of Labor, 1920-38 (Box 456, Folder 13)
        - Wages and hours
          - Fair Labor Standards Act
            - 1911-41 (Box 456, Folder 14-16)
            - 1942-69 (Box 457, Folder 1-6)
          - Guaranteed annual wage, 1955-58, n.d. (Box 457, Folder 7)
          - Minimum wage
            - National, 1974-77 (Box 457, Folder 8)
            - New York State, 1936-42 (Box 457, Folder 9)
          - Portal to Portal Pay Act, 1947 (Box 457, Folder 10)
          - Walsh-Healy Act (Public contracts), 1935-42 (Box 457, Folder 11)
        - YWCA and unions, 1933-47, n.d. (Box 457, Folder 12-15)
      - Liquor control, 1922-41 (Box 457, Folder 16-18)
      - Price control
        - Economic stabilization: Defense Production Act
          - General, 1951-53 (Box 458, Folder 1)
          - Rent control, 1946-53 (Box 458, Folder 2-3)
        - Hearings on cost of living, 1947-48 (Box 458, Folder 4)
        - Office of Price Administration, 1940-46, n.d. (Box 458, Folder 5-11)
      - Recreation
        - General, 1945-46 (Box 458, Folder 12)
        - Surplus property, 1958-59 (Box 458, Folder 13)
      - Rural
        - Agricultural economic and social problems, 1929-54 (Box 458, Folder 14-16)
        - Aid to farmers, 1940-58 (Box 459, Folder 1-2)
      - Social Security
        - General, 1932-56 (Box 459, Folder 3)
        - Food stamps, 1940-41, 1971-77 (Box 459, Folder 4)
        - Health care for the aged
          - General, 1958-70 (Box 459, Folder 5-10)
          - Correspondence with American Medial Association, 1961-62 (Box 459, Folder 11)
          - Community YWCAs, 1961-63 (Box 459, Folder 12)
          - Organization and Corporation statements, A-Z, 1961-63 (Box 459, Folder 13-15)
        - Old age pensions, 1929-35 (Box 459, Folder 16)
        - Social Security Act of 1935
          - General, 1934-36 (Box 460, Folder 1)
          - Amendments, 1936-77 (Box 460, Folder 2-13)
          - Benefits for women, 1960-98 (Box 460, Folder 14)
        - Social insurance for non-profit organizations, 1935-65 (Box 461, Folder 1-7)
        - Unemployment insurance, 1929-40 (Box 461, Folder 8-9)
        - Welfare, [see Social Security Act of 1935-Amendments] (Box 461)
      - Taxation
        - General, 1946-80 (Box 461, Folder 10)
        - Tax-exempt status of YWCA, 1941-74 (Box 461, Folder 11-12)
      - Trade policies
        - Monopolies, 1943-49 (Box 461, Folder 13)
        - Reciprocal trade agreements
          - 1932-40 (Box 461, Folder 14)
          - 1943-74, n.d. (Box 462, Folder 1-7)
      - Women
        - General, 1963-75 (Box 462, Folder 8)
        - Status of women
          - General, 1962-75 (Box 462, Folder 9)
          - Equal Rights Amendment
            - 1921-45 (Box 462, Folder 10-13)
            - 1946-83 (Box 463, Folder 1-11)
          - Women's Bureau, 1941-75 (Box 463, Folder 12-14)
      - Women workers
        - General, 1915-96 (Box 464, Folder 1-2)
        - Equal economic rights for women, 1969-73, 1998 (Box 464, Folder 3)
        - Equal Employment Opportunities Commission, 1965-72 (Box 464, Folder 4-5)
        - Equal pay for equal work, 1938-74 (Box 464, Folder 6-11)
        - Married women at work, 1929-41 (Box 464, Folder 12)
        - Pregnant women at work, 1977 (Box 464, Folder 13)
        - Protective labor legislation, 1962-71 (Box 464, Folder 14)
        - State labor legislation, 1949-71 (Box 465, Folder 1-2)
        - Virgin Islands, 1935-36 (Box 465, Folder 3)
    - Youth
      - General, 1933-77 (Box 465, Folder 4-9)
      - Employment opportunities, 1940-75 (Box 465, Folder 10-11)
      - Juvenile justice and delinquency
        - 1946-58 (Box 465, Folder 12-13)
        - 1959-79, 1997 (Box 466, Folder 1-4)
      - Vote for eighteen-year-olds, 1954-71 (Box 466, Folder 5)